if you are interested in GrandMA 3 macros this
is the right video for you and what are macros
macros according to the GrandMA 3 manual
are commands stored in the pool object the
commands can be very complex or they can be very
simple and they can be everything in between
macros can make programming faster and more
convenient and macros can make it possible
to do trivial or complex operations by a simple
push of a button macros are stored in the macro
pool but can be assigned to physical keys and
view buttons so if you see here i opened a
our macro pool here and there's no macros
right now if you watch the last episode we
used the macro to load some predefined faces but
this time we're going to load some predefined
macros the GrandMA 3 when you open it up doesn't
have any predefined macros in it so you have to to
go in and find them import the ones you need and
and forget about the rest and it's quite simple
if you go over here and hover and push it down and
use our swipes and say edit we open up this window
here and as you can see i opened it up on our
screen number two we can just enlarge it a little
bit here if you don't know how to do that you
simply push it up here and decides where to open
it up and then it opens up in a separate window
it's a little bit easier to to watch and see how
everything is done there we go so we have our new
macro lineup here and we have all these confusing
things down here but what you need to know in
the beginning is just to import a predefined
macro and what you do is you you you push it up
here new macro line and you say import down here
you push it and then you have all these macros
coming up all these pre-defined GrandMA 3 macros
so what we can do is say okay what do we need
we need maybe a store button so we simply type
store here or start typing store and then you
can see the different options that comes up each
of these is a separate macro we just need a simple
store command so we choose this one and say import
when we close the window down you can see here
it already labeled it this is now a store macro
so what we can do with it is to just clear out the
programmer and say okay we choose all our vipers
we turn them on at full we put them in a position
we maybe give them a color and we want to store
it somewhere previously when we stored something
we would go up here and open the command section
we would push store here and then we will close
it down again and then we will decide where to
store it you could also use the shortcuts if you
turn on the shortcut menu down here and once again
go in here and you can see all the shortcuts here
and you can see store shortcut is s so depending
on the way you want to work there's a lot of
different ways to do this right now we have our
store macro and we put something in the programmer
which is all our vipers in a color and a position
and we need to store it somewhere up here so now
we can simply say store and then up here push one
of the buttons up here and that is a store command
so this one this store macro works exactly like
the store button on the physical console remember
if you like what you see here consider liking the
video and maybe even subscribing to the channel
that way you're going to get a notification next
time we upload a video but let's see what else
we can find in here let's do the next one we
push it down we drag it outside the box and
we say edit and say what else would we need
let's say we might want to have a highlight
button so we search for highlight we find it and
we import it close this one down and now we have
a highlight button we don't want it right here oh
sorry we don't want it right here we want to move
it somewhere else so we say move maybe over here
and we take the store button as well and we
move that down here so here we could have
a next button for instance so we push it down
drag it out and say edit we import we search for
we search for next like this and we just need a
simple next button right here we close it down and
we say if we have a next button we need a previous
button as well do the same thing edit import
we search for previous if we could spell
there we go previous we import that one
and we close it down so now we have a next and
a previous button we have a store and highlight
so what is highlight we can just push it right
now and you can see everything goes white up here
because highlight takes all the moving lights
and take all the colors gobos everything out of
it so you can identify the right fixture if you
want to work with it and then you can simply say
next next next next or previous previous previous
this works exactly the same as if you push the
previous and the next button up here so what else
do we need maybe we need an align button or key we
use the align down here all the time where we push
this one in some of the previous episodes maybe
it's clever to have an align on and another line
off so let's just see what we can import we have
a line off right here so let's just import that
one and that would be the equivalent of choosing
off right down here and then let's see if we can
find the other align tool which one is that that
is the align rotate i am pretty sure it is there
it is yes so now we can say instead of choosing
it down here we can simply push it up here and you
can see it's on the the dash right here the rotate
the one we used all the time and we can say off on
this one so as you can see you can use macros for
very simple tasks but if you want to work
directly on a touchscreen and you don't uh
especially if you're working on the granima 3 on
pc version it's really clever to to to get as much
up on the screen as possible because then you
can better and you can work faster so what i've
just shown you here is macros GrandMA 3 macros
in its simplest form macros can be incredibly
complex and they can be thousands and thousands
of lines of code if you want to that all depends
on what you want to do but basically you can
ask the disk to do almost anything with macros
in the next video linked on the screen right now
i'm gonna go deeper into macros and and into how
you can use them to do more complex everyday tasks
so when that one is ready it's going to be linked
up here until then it's going to be one of the
other videos from our channel and if you like
anything you have seen today please like the video
and maybe even consider subscribing to the channel
that way you're going to get a notification every
time we upload a new video in this GrandMA 3
programming tutorial series so thank you for
watching and i hope to see you next time bye bye